[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Jeff dittle I'm
excited to invite Chuck weindorf as our
guest on the show today for a
conversation about leaders and software
engineers Chuck is a retired IT director
and chief engineer with nearly 40 years
of experience in software engineering he
encourages software Engineers to
understand their responsibilities see
their value adapt to change and focus on
future Direction with stories and humor
he influences software Engineers to
excel in their craft Chuck is the author
of the book leaders and software
Engineers which is the topic for this
episode Chuck welcome to the show hi
Jeff it's great to be here I've been
looking forward to this me too so tell
us what encouraged you to write this
book leaders and software Engineers well
I was an amateur writer as part of my
part-time fund while I was making an
earning as a software engineer and I got
a flare for being able to communicate to
my peer Engineers on the happenings and
what was going on when I stepped into
leadership it became a weekly article so
I would communicate with 200 and some
engineers and 700 folks in it through
this email and the demands of it hey
keep adding to my mailing list so the
company was passed around quite a bit
and the things that that I like to focus
on were the things that helped other
folks understand Engineers from the
outside so not only were we encouraging
Engineers to do their best work was also
helping the organization understand how
to work with Engineers because
personality types were were somewhat
rare and very unique in in the business
place okay so you had some experience
basically writing the book or elements
of the book I imagine just as a natural
part of your career
yes it so it is a compilation so it over
about three years of Articles written
within the company I was working with
and encouraging engineers then became uh
once I was nearing retirement I began to
assemble those stories into a how did
you end up as a software leader my
journey to a software leader came from
the ground up so came right out of high
school as a hobbyist and I was making
pong type games and the like with a home
computer went down to a company and they
just says I make these programs you guys
do any of this down here and company was
Area Insurance in are my local town and
they yeah we got big mainframes here so
I I came up that channel where I was
constantly learning new things and
Technologies each new technology that
came out I was jumping into it folks
began to let's say follow along with my
career so a group of folks who were
like-minded began to do that till the
point where I'd reach in my 40s and they
said look you really ought to be in the
in the formal leadership track now let's
move you over into that role but we want
you to stay technical so I had that
wonderful experience of of being able to
learn new technologies be an evangelist
for them and be able to encourage others
to try them and really helped the
company move ahead this company was was
very traditional and so took a little
extra effort to get them to try new
technology so that was my leadership
role was maybe being the first penguin
to jump in the water and if I don't get
eat by all the killer whales then great
other folks jumping great and I'm sure
we'll get to that more in the show as we
talk about the career trajectory of a
lot of software Engineers because I
imagine some of our listeners have a
similar experience of starting with a
technical background and then eventually
they find themselves in a position of
formal leadership which can be
challenging at times so the book is
organized around four major content
areas people responsibilities culture
and Leadership and I want to make sure
we get a little bit of time on each of
those topics so let's start from the
very beginning in the book you talk
about the engineer personality so give
us a sense of why four where these four
came from and then let's talk about them
a little bit and how they play out in
the real world in your experience the
four personalities more or less came
just just by experience I kept coming
across the same categories of
individuals in in the course of my
career and it didn't matter if they were
my age or they're much younger we seem
to to fit in four categories that are a
little non-traditional I'd say I would
categorize them in ways that of their
Behavior so the first personality was
the genius category and in it the folks
that go into it can have some very high
IQs and with that comes an internal
thought that I must be right you know
I'm smarter as guy in the room therefore
I'm probably the one saying the right
things and and my ideas are probably the
right ones so there is with each of
these personality types there's a
technique I need to help improve their
performance so Geniuses high IQ is is
their thing the allstars are those folks
who are more natural to the Technologies
and can do the most difficult work and
they tend to gravitate the difficult
work and the challenges for them might
be to how do I get that knowledge out of
their heads and into other talented
people's heads because they're so
focused on getting the worst things
fixed and the best things done sometimes
how do they help interact with the team
and bring others along the introvert
category is another one these folks have
that ability to concentrate
at a super deep level so they can go
down to the minute parts of the code and
do fantastic
things and they may have some of the
best ideas of our entire group so how do
we work with folks who are introverted
and fide the room down so an introvert
might be able to say their idea so that
everyone can hear it this is like the
backbone of the lines of code if I'm
going to say about millions of lines of
code I've seen in my career that group
really produces a lot of work
and then finally the this is a bit of a
wild card group I call it Uncommon Sense
anytime communicating with Engineers I
find that they just hear things
different than the average person and
they answer things maybe in a very
literal way or in a unconventional way
and so I have to be specific in my
communication with folks who are
listening with their Uncommon Sense
filter and probably some of the most
entertaining stories come from that well
speaking of stories can you give us some
examples of how each of those
personalities has maybe played out in
some real world scenarios that you've
experienced sure I I give you a brief
one for each of those the genius
category there was an Oldtimer who is
about my age and always excellent
thinking but always had I'm always right
is also the challenge so how do I
convince this individual to do something
I grab a marker and we had just put
those
wall-sized wallpaper on the wallpaper
you could write on with with markers
well this guy know that we had put those
things up there I grab this marker and
start writing on what looks like a white
wall and he's just jumping up hey genius
you're writing on the wall you know and
and it just never occurred to him that
somebody might actually you know have
other reasons to do things and so we
always started off with hey I'm I'm
always right I'm going to call people
out on it and it was just okay slow down
a little let's let's go through the
steps of it and then let's let's then
dig into your thinking so I can
understand how deep you've gone into it
as well so so this individual that's
really all it took is like okay now calm
down we're going to go through the steps
so that was always a good trigger for
that conversation for the All-Star
category these people are so talented
and can do some of the most difficult
tasks the trick for them is to to help
them understand the interns the other
software Engineers are just coming into
a technology you've really got to bring
them along and I almost think you have
to trick them into doing it in some hey
we're going to have a pizza party you're
going to present to us how you've done
this really difficult piece of code so
it give them a spotlight to Showcase
their talents and then it made them
easier to begin to share so I would be
able to to draw out from them all this
Talent if I just gave them the The Forum
and then they can get the Adoration of
the the less experienced folks are think
well that's that's really
great for our introverts category the
thing I really need to do is to slow the
conversations down for them so there was
one individual who's who Maybe been on
the autistic spectrum and he was so
brilliant it was It was kind of Beyond
understanding sometimes what he was
thinking and he would make a a statement
well I think we should do this this
really unconventional thing and they're
like okay now we're all GNA stop and
we're quiet the whole room down and says
can you tell us in small words you know
what exactly brings you to that and uh
kind of making it a safe space let's say
that uh I'm I'm going to hold folks
responsible for staying quiet we had a
Talking Stick if I hold a Talking Stick
you got to let let me talk and that is
one thing I would do with this
particular introvert is you hold that
and no one will interrupt you and then
he was comfortable sharing the detail of
the idea two-thirds of the time we ended
up with something highly valuable from
that process and finally Uncommon Sense
we would have uh folks come in and I
somebody coming in from overseas who had
that Uncommon Sense filter I told them I
got in on on the ground floor of
engineering and for two years he thought
I worked on the first floor of the
building when I when I joined the
company I said no no it's it's it's the
ground floor another person I said hey
look at the color of that house that's a
really unusual color and he says yeah
this this side of the house looks like
it's colored orange or something and I
says why'd you say this side of the
house well I don't know what the other
side of the house is painted right well
it's it isn't it the same well I
couldn't assume that because the
Uncommon Sense filter said maybe that's
not what it is and so I had to be
somewhat specific in make sure my
sentence had a subject and a verb and a
predicate that all worked together and
it was very clear because the filters of
The Uncommon Sense might change what
they're hearing have you found ways to
help those different types of
personalities overcome some of those
challenges in communicating have you
been able to help them to also find ways
to interact together in more effective
ways absolutely the Advent of agile and
scrum and all these other types of more
collaborative team efforts has helped a
lot so on occasion I can give that
Allstar hey you're going to do some very
formative work you're going to go to
this level but you're going to coach
another to do a complex task and that
seem to be a good match or I'm gonna
assign the genius some of the technical
documentation responsibilities okay well
I I know you know it and I know you've
got this great depth for it but you need
to get it into words that you can in
help you're as a technical writer you're
going to to explain your world to them
it comes down to
what are you really good at and having
them understand what they they have and
their skills and talents and then what
can you share to others and vice versa
what sort of things can you gain from
from these others are in the interor
category we had an individual who could
do insurance rating down to the 2000th
field of detail and know how it worked
well we really didn't even have folks in
our our user Community understand all of
what their rating formulas did in some
cases and so giving them the the ability
to say hey here's here's the important
factors in rating might be a very great
conversation to listen to them and so I
think it comes down to having that that
really open conversation around a table
agile is great for that having the daily
standup where we can get hey what did
you really do yesterday that was was
awesome and exciting okay well then that
began to share with others what some
ideas for their own work they might be
able to employ so that that I've really
like the the agile model to help teams
with so what do you say if somebody says
that these four types are maybe a bit
simplistic or
reductionistic well it certainly is I'd
like to say I'm in the genius category I
even asked my son about that because
he's an engineer also like n it didn't
it didn't make that but he does say
you've got that weird Uncommon Sense
filer sometimes sometimes people have to
tell you something twice did I do some
All-Star work sure I did and did I tell
somebody to go away because I want to
work five hours straight on a problem as
an introvert sure I did so yes the
categories are really flexible they're
just to call out maybe some of the
pitfalls we have as engineers in our
personalities and maybe we have an
element of each in a way it's just to
get people thinking about hey I I'm a
bit like that I do those things too
maybe I can try some of these techniques
that will improve me in my in my job and
and our team also yeah and I appreciate
that technique focus and like I said
before the show you know the old adage
all models are wrong but some are useful
so that's what really matters at the end
of the
day well great
so as you're talking about people you
actually mentioned a few things that you
might do with those different
personality types as far as helping them
with particular responsibilities to help
maximize their strengths and maybe
mitigate some of their challenges that
come along with that personality type so
let's shift gears and talk about
responsibilities which is the next major
section in the book and the first
responsibility that you mention the
title of the section is quality is the
goal where the is all caps so let's talk
about why quality is the goal as it
pertains to software leadership and
responsibilities this might be my my
hardest one lesson over the the lifetime
of providing software the mistakes in
software are magnified by maybe 10,000
users 100,000 users can see how dumb we
can be sometimes and that that really is
a bad day we can build a a system with
300,000 lines of good code however the
Trust In us is going to erode if we make
one significant mistake and and folks
understand new software does some
strange things but really will lose
their trust quickly if this continues so
quality is is the really the only thing
I can hang my hat on to say I'm a
programming success as far as software
development that if they can depend on
this app to do their job better and
improve their day to make a customer
service or whatever element of the
business that this software does if if
it works well so if it's effective in
its job that's primary and I don't
negotiate on that if there are some
defects one team that was was mired in
defects I said okay here's the deal if a
severity defect of level two which was
fairly High comes in by the next release
and we were an agile team so it was five
six days away we're gonna fix this no
discussion I don't care what else Waits
we're going to fix these things for
Quality the high quality systems then
all of a sudden work begins to come to
you from others it's the fun work it's
the new and exciting it's maybe new
features to your system enhancements
that the business would really crave you
get to work on that and and you're not
just doing the whacka mole of hitting
this defect and that defect and now you
fix one defect and another pops up so
what you mentioned before you said you
had a team with a lot of defects and if
a certain level of severity came in what
happened as a result of that when you
sort of implemented that zero tolerance
for defects policy well they got a
annoyed pretty quickly and I do think
there's a healthy annoyance that we can
provide to everyone is that look I'm
going to disrupt your day if your
quality is not good because now you're
gonna have to sit and listen to the old
manager come in and say all right we're
going to stop doing everything we're go
back and and redo this thing we thought
we were done with not to say that we
were making it public but internal to
the team we almost had a little bit of a
scoreboard going on all right who's
stuck working on the def that they
created from the last release and it
became um let's see it's like the GU
landing on the aircraft carrier
everyone's knowing who's hitting the
second wire on the on the aircraft
carrier every time and everybody knows
who's missing with the hook and has to
circle around and go and so that
internal competition was healthy because
once we got down to where we were fixing
them each release for some reason they
stopped showing up we've got fewer and
fewer significant ones because folks did
a little bit extra on their enhancements
I'm going to make sure it's working I'm
going to go back and do regression work
I'm going to automate some tests so I
can make sure this is good forever all
those habits were good simply by making
visible how good our quality was or our
lack of quality even more important
sounds like from what you just said that
there's a relationship between
responsibility and
accountability there is I always
struggled with whether I'm responsible
or accountable for something and I say
isn't a lot easier if if the work is
good you can say I did both or I'm
really I'm really counting both as a
success as a leader I always knew I was
accountable for a couple hundred people
in a way and the responsibility of this
gang was to to give me high quality when
those things were going good then folks
are rewarded we're all celebrated the
world gets easier when quality is high
because those other things fallen and
you have more time to do the fun stuff
because you're not dealing with those
other things 100% 100 per. this this job
can be very enjoyable and and rewarding
there hey you're making something out of
nothing how many people get to do that
and if your customers are are excited
coming to you with new ideas that you
didn't think of obviously and it's
helping the business you are going to
have a real enjoyable career across the
board it's it's less like work yeah in
fact I'd even say in a way we're making
nothing from nothing because it's just
ones and zeros it it is it is getting
down to the the very uh the root of it I
I I did program a little binary a 100
years ago so wait you programmed binary
not assembler binary okay no I even went
that far back I was I was doing some
kind of encryption thing at the time so
I got to go through the ones and zeros
well if this was a different episode
topic I might want to chase that rabbit
but for now we're gonna move on okay
sounds good that'll be the bside from
after the show okay so also in this
section of responsibilities you
mentioned something that is near and
dear to my heart I know it is to yours
as well which is ethics so let's talk
about the ethics of software engineering
and software leadership from your
perspective I learned my attention to
ethics a couple ways one one was from my
dad you know who was a military man Navy
guy and when I got to the company as a
19yearold the folks who were in the most
senior positions were the World War II
guys and talk about ethics ethics is
wired into these people I mean some of
them were toddlers during a depression
so they didn't have a lot and when they
did a job well they didn't have to Crow
about it they would tell me constantly
hey don't complain you know we we beat
the furer we beat the emperor
you know what you're doing is kind of
easy I'm like oh yeah I guess you're
right so for me ethics came to having an
attention that if everyone saw what I
was doing in my day and they saw you're
doing okay then that would be a good
habit to get in place for engineers back
in the day I could pick up the master
file for our company $250 million of
data in three reels pick it up walking
around the room do all sorts of things
and so the ethics that they were giving
to it the time a 20-year-old you know
the the charge of Ethics to me was you
got to take care of this stuff this is
the company's life BL and so today when
someone is is let's say fixing a
production defect and they get elevated
authority to go into a production system
and actually look at what's going on
there and that sort of thing I have to
be able to trust that they're not gonna
go and pull up the owner of the
company's bio and and see what policies
he holds or other things so ethics
becomes very important to me to say this
data that you're touching and the
information you have access to is so
precious that any kind of a breach of
this information or and this trust is
just fatal to organizations so I have to
I have to work on the ethics my own
ethics the ethics of everyone in my
field and to let them know this is a
non-negotiable we're going to perform at
the highest ethical level and if there
are problems that we detect we're going
to elevate them and talk about them and
handle them a me so how have you
instilled you mentioned a little bit
about quality but maybe more broadly how
have you worked to instill those kinds
of values in the teams that you've
worked with in your career for Quality I
I I tried to lead by example in in one
of my projects it was a a complex
document replacement so insurance
documents lots of rules lots of laws and
all sorts of things on it many moving
Parts hundreds of data fields so it was
easy to miss stuff and you couldn't
because you go into a court of law and
if something wasn't right you really
didn't do well so what we did was we we
were early adop adopter of automation
repeatable automation the most common
policy send them through get your
documents compare them to the last time
tell what's changed and then our work
directly with quality assurance to say
this change was intended is that good
they give it a thumbs up and then we
would make that our new automated test
going forward so not only did we start
doing that but we said all requirements
had to match the actual system all the
time so this was many system systems
would start with requirements but then
bug fixes would go in and small
enhancements and we wouldn't document
them the same way they'd be in different
places and I said nope none of that you
open up this document and you're going
to see what the production system is
doing at all time so that level for
Quality that made a big difference
because there was no discussion about
well who asked for this and is that the
right thing the system was well
documented down to its production level
all times so for Quality that was
probably my best example of all we were
ble to get down to singled digigit
defects in a series of hundreds of
documents I actually want to pause there
for a second I think that's a really
important Insight that often can be
missed in our industry so maybe talk a
little bit more about that specifically
about how documentation and quality go
together because I think there's a lot
of sense from certain corners of the
industry about things like my code is
self-documenting or phrases like that
that are sort of bandied about and yet
you just made a really strong
correlation between excellent
documentation and quality a little bit
of my I understand where the oldtimers
come from and the the level of
documentation used to do to these
systems back in the day and it was
functional documentation when you need
to make a change to it you do these
things each time we had less of the
formal written document and now the the
newer techniques which is agile I've
done 7,000 story cards what does the
system look like as a whole well I don't
know it's 7,000 story cards okay well
that makes me nervous because defect
comes in and they said hey we we think
the system should do this I'm like oh my
gosh what story card was that can I call
that a defect or is that a new
enhancement so it was important for team
efficiency of an Enterprise team serving
we've served 12 business units look
we're going to have the document precise
and when the document is incorrect we
fix the document then we fix the
application and it always went in that
order if there was something in the
document that was correct and we saw the
document didn't produce properly there's
your defect it was such an easy way to
go about business because we all agreed
on where we started developer didn't do
it properly you fix it the new
requirement coming from the business you
add it to the requirements and schedule
it and so it it became just mechanically
simple and we didn't have to go hunt and
Peck for what was the system really
supposed to be doing whenever we went
and had a let's say a challenge a legal
challenge to how our our operation went
whenever we were audited we could prove
what we were doing I mean it just made
life so much easier now it's effort it's
hours and it's attention to detail and
you need the business's help to make
that document but it was so worthwhile
and there's the other time that wasn't
measured which is all the pain and
suffering you didn't endure because you
had the document it reminds me somewhat
of how in the construction industry they
have as builts there's the original
designs but then they keep updating the
designs as they go so that when you're
done you know exactly how the building
was built which is really useful for
maintaining the building which kind of
pertains to Quality we actually stole a
a construction term but punch list was a
a term that came from a construction
side thing and we actually have a side
punch list to say here's how you're
going to change your application outside
of the original requirements I'm like oh
man I hate that so we tried to Wrangle
that back into the mainstream that very
important people asking for enhancements
still came in through the front door and
didn't just virally happen in our system
and then how about ethics you know
that's of those where instilling ethics
in people sounds like an interesting
proposition but I'm I'm curious what
you've done in your career to try to
help enhance that with the teams you've
worked
with I've been in interviews with with
so many candidates whether they're
experienced or right out of school or uh
overseas and all sorts of of things and
and I'm listening with my my ears to
hear are what you're telling me accurate
about yourself and I'm asking some
leading questions hey in this situation
what would you do how would you handle
this and most of the answers are
well-intentioned but I also think some
of them are let's say I want I don't
want to make myself look terrible and so
there there has to be an element of look
you got to tell me when you make
mistakes I'm not going to Club we're
going to work together on this we'll
have a we'll have a true up conversation
later about how we can improve
performance but you're going to be able
to approach me at any time and tell me
things that you are worried about it in
an ethical sense now if it's if I was a
heavy-handed manager and I'm I'm just
got a tight grip on every activity that
the team does I'm not going to have that
trust from the individuals to try and
hey here's something that's really going
wrong I'm going to try and fix it so
Chuck doesn't find out those were always
bad days so I was listening in
interviews to say how's this this
individual behave are they going to be
open with their own failings and when
things go wrong and I'm going to also
try and admit when I am wrong which
happens all the time and I'm to say hey
look I'm still here it's been 40 years
look you can make a mistake and still be
okay here but you've got to come clean
and the folks who could be very
confident in themselves to come forward
with problems and be able to tell me I
felt we the most ethical individuals
that kind of at their root and then we
could build on that then we could build
on information security and data quality
and those other things that we're
charged with here's why we have to
protect these things but if they had it
in their heart to be an ethical
individual then that was a great start
well I think that's a really interesting
segue too it's almost like you planned
the book to to kind of flow through
because you're starting to talk a little
bit about culture which is the next
session of the book and I think there's
a really interesting correlation there
between the culture you create and the
behaviors of the people and how they act
within that culture in ethical or
non-ethical ways so with that in mind
let's talk a little bit about culture
why culture is important let's start
there Fant fantastic I I was fortunate
enough my first big big full-time job
was with an insurance company it really
was still run by the original founding
family was still working there and so I
heard right from the people who founded
the place what their culture was going
to be like and when I was listening to
that I was like this is great I gotta I
got to remember this I gotta write this
down and one of the themes was above all
in service well that's easier and the
word service has the word Eerie inside
of it so there you go I should be able
to remember that so just the very basics
of being above all in service for them
was to be very clear in helping uh the
policy holder or the agency and to
communicate with each other let's enlist
to help of others in the company to do
that same thing two people could succeed
at the same job which was wonderful that
culture meant I can do good you can do
good and we're both going to be rewarded
there was less of a hey only one person
can be rewarded this year ethic to it it
they would just be able through through
the culture to encourage everyone to do
well and the company went from quite
small to Fortune 500 over the course of
10 years that was really impressive but
it was done based on employee loyalty
and Longevity was what really gave them
their their competitive Advantage so I
think that the culture of the
organization starting off is key because
the leaders then that they bring in to
say here's the people that are going to
carry this culture out need to be in and
same mind you have to do the things the
way the culture is designed that made
this business a success so for me I was
fortunate I had a great team that
brought me in taught me the ropes set
the bar very high but also in the times
where I knocked the bar off the off the
rail they'd come and help me put it back
on and said now you're not gonna do that
again are you I once misprinted 1,000
forms with a little X that didn't quite
fit in the box that it had to be in and
uh rather than reprint the forms to
teach me something they gave me a black
pen and I went and I exed off the box
for about 800 of those 10,000 forms and
that was the the comment from my
supervisor well you're not gonna make
that mistake again it's like you're
right you taught me something and that
was the last I heard of it except for I
write in the book and talk about it for
40 years later but the culture was great
that way you could talk about the things
the challenges that you had and and it
was okay if you looked a little silly or
if you you could talk about your
mistakes it didn't penalize
so how about people who find themselves
in maybe a more challenging culture and
how would you encourage somebody who's
in leadership in a software company to
address that kind of a situation and
maybe build culture or change culture
Yeah It's Tricky there are other
organizations where let's say your
margin is tight you don't have a cash
Reserve to make a lot of mistakes that's
where the the manager or maybe your
resources are limited you don't have
enough people really do the adequate job
that I've described so the the
documentation and the and the automated
testing are not as mature the manager
really has to in that case manage up in
the organization I've got to break down
the CEO's door and I gotta come in and
say hey look we're just going to be in a
bad way if we don't do certain things
right and maybe picking your battle with
with that group is is the right way to
put it and to take the high road so the
ethics the quality how do I keep that as
as Paramount and maybe we have to work
some overtime to get some of these
things done so the time management hurts
for a little bit but I'll bring it back
so I think it's the manager's job not
only to go to their leaders and say
here's how we're going to run the
railroad they also have to come down to
their team and say hey look we got each
other's back right we're not going to be
sniping at each other we've go we've got
to do this properly between all of us so
in a way sometimes it becomes a this
team against the world mentality but you
have to have that for the folks who work
every day you know they're they've got
you and uh that they're going to help
you through the day you can build some
of that culpture within your individual
teams but you've got to let the guys at
the top know hey're we're doing things a
little differently and you can't come
down on us too hard it'll break the the
momentum we have yeah and I think that
speaks some to the protective aspect of
a of a engineering manager or a software
leader generally is helping to protect
the team from things that might make the
team challenged to struggle frustrated
these kinds of things it seems to be
easy to do and in some markets sometimes
Engineers are in very high demand and
you could lose top talent very easily if
the culture shifts to where they they
feel like either they're not valued
they're not rewarded or they're becoming
a scapegoat for the things that are
outside of their control if any of that
happens you're going to lose some Grue
one of the things you talk about as it
pertains to culture is communication so
what's the connection in your experience
between those two concepts
Communications this journey became when
I was in a room of 17 Engineers we had
locked doors we were kind of an
extension of the computer room the
computer room had all these big security
things on it you had to pass things
through in writing to get us to do
anything and people would see the
engineers and in the lunchroom and not
come and talk to us or anything because
we were those people so I think that it
was really important that communication
had to get more broad between engineers
and other elements of the company just
to be say hey we're on the same team
we're trying to help you and we don't
understand what you're asking for
sometimes so we need better
Communications to understand how to do
this best within it then there became
those little silos and factions that
said hey we're the infrastructure team
we do Network wiring and that's it well
that's great your Network's slow in this
in this note and I don't know why can I
help have them help me identify the
problems and get things done a
communication channels between the silos
were so important so for for my part of
it I was trying to find people who I
could talk to in the other areas of the
company that I could just just have the
very straightforward ones and zeros kind
of conversation like here's what I see
and we're having trouble can you help me
that then grew to the communications of
not I should tell everybody the good
things we're doing in in this area of
the company and Engineering in in
particular and let's tell them about the
things we're not doing good at others
tended to show up and start help us then
so communication really gave others
understanding of here's the successes we
can provide to you and here's the things
we're struggling with that you can help
us with and if I wasn't communicating
then I was still just that really young
guy locked in the back room not
understanding why I was doing certain
things in my code I just figured there'd
be a smarter person telling me to do
this on purpose well I became more of
the solution once I started
communicating there speak to a little
bit because one of the sections of the
book you talk about optimism versus
pessimism and yet you just talked about
highlighting the problems so how do you
uh cut a
reconcile that I say I'm an optimist but
I have a slight pessimistic streak so
there's the streak that says if there's
any problem in the system I did
it it must be me so I checked my stuff
first you know that was my pessimistic
Street I just had solar panels put on
the house this month guess what happened
this month a month ago well we had an
eclipse I lost three minutes of sunshine
so I'm out there complaining about yeah
I just got these solar panels on the
house now there's an eclipse over my
house unhealthy PES which is that and
then there's healthy pessimism which is
I should double check my work maybe I
made a mistake if I heard something's a
problem I better look at my in the
mirror first but then there's optimism
the optimism is hey what's what's that
end view if I go to heaven what's this
look like this system how good is it
going to be when we're all done with it
sure there's going to be potholes and
other things but the optimism says I
have a vision of where I want to get to
so optimism isn't we just don't think
we're going to make a mistake that's the
unhealthy of op so each has an element
each of the stories I try and and tell
is hey here's somebody who's over
optimistic and here's somebody who's
over pessimistic in the wrong ways I say
will you people try and and be positive
for once this guy says I still don't
think the system's gonna work look try a
positive way to to say that I'm positive
this ain't gonna work I saw that coming
yeah and so it's just how do you
transform that right and sometimes it's
just letting them vent their pessimism
and then we get back on to work great I
could live with that but the continual
over optimism continual over pessimism
is going to slow the team down and
that's what I tried to work to Modern
yeah I tell software Engineers a lot
they say our job is to be near-term
pessimists midterm realists and
long-term optimists so it sounds like
we've got a similar view but I I
appreciate the self-reflectivity about
that as well that start with maybe the
problem's me I think that's a really
interesting cultural element there that
that I think is good to cultivate for
sure I think most of my sports work that
way too went and got new bowling shoes
new bowling ball new bowling glove tape
on my finger and all that and I still
had the same uh the same average and and
one of the guys my team like I think the
problem's between your ears yeah that's
right he right that's right well you
know we Engineers we have our jokes like
the the pebcak which is problem exists
between keyboard and chair right the the
pebcak error So Lonely at the Top yes it
is that's right one of the things you
also talk about as it pertains to
culture is the Old Guard versus new
Engineers so tell us a little bit about
your experience and what you mean with
that
phrase what I found is that the the old
guard and the new Talent both have
wonderful Minds for automation they just
approach it very differently and the Old
Guard will fall into that hey this this
old way of doing things is might be the
only way to do things or it's I've
proved it out that it's the best because
it's stood the test of time at the same
time there are some programs and
software out there that are decades old
that still work excellently so I need
the knowledge of the Old Guard to bring
others along and to be able to maintain
these systems and to understand how they
work and and why were they good what why
does this work well uh so the Old Guard
has that knowledge of Legacy systems
which we have many Legacy applications
in the world uh and it's important that
they share that knowledge and they they
teach us the basics as a younger uh
generation on the practice is good it
high quality is still good high
performance is still good uh redundancy
of systems is good and so all those
things that they've learned the hard way
I need them to share that information
but also open their mind to the new
techniques that are coming through uh
agile was a bit of a war getting them to
try that that was you mean I got to tell
these other people what I did yesterday
I like yeah it's just it's G to help
people to hear it well the the new
talent that comes in might be hey I've
got this latest tool or toy and it's
great and it works for uh these
particular roles and both sides seem to
be able to say my favorite tech can do
anything therefore I'm gonna use it as a
screwdriver and a hammer and a wrench
and a you know all right guys hey look
we we have to be let's say Let's Pretend
We're All Architects for a day and say
what would be the best place to put this
tool or that tool so to have the new
Talent learn some of the old
Technologies is always a challenge and
to encourage them to do that and I've
actually you know rewarded with bonuses
some folks who have taken that leap hey
I'm going to go back and learn some of
the old Tech I'm like okay well we need
that at the same time we've incentivized
some of the old guard to step step
forward do the teaching but also turn
themselves back into a trainee and learn
for example low coat was one thing I did
I had a couple Old-Timers jump in there
and get their basic certification
they're like hey I don't hate this okay
well then now we're making progress it's
too easy to draw the line between one
generation another and want hey I know
what I know how to do this don't tell me
anything else and then the Young Folks
like you old guys use that old Tech but
this new Tech's far better well it's you
know there's elements of Truth to both
but you all got to work together these
systems are hybrids and that new tech is
going to be old Tech in about 10 years
and so it's gonna happen again you just
hit one of my favorite topics that I
would say in a meetings an Oldtimer is
talking about hey here we've done this
this way for years and here's why we do
it because it's good and one of the
young guys saying like you're just
saying that because that's the only
thing you know and I says Hey in 20
years are you sitting on that side of
the table or are you telling me that c
is like the only way to do this maybe I
am and so it's it's like hey this this
career is a journey you're G to be in
that chair someday so try and understand
the journey when you get there yeah you
talked a little bit about rewards and
incentives just there can you speak a
little bit more to how those shape
culture yeah they're they're a two-edged
sword in a way the recognition is very
important and and you're recognizing
specific things we aren't all on a
conveyor belt putting Parts together and
I said hey I did 10 more parts than the
other guy I might do less lines of code
but I might have done something
brilliant so it really is very
subjective to the leadership to be able
to look at things and say I want to
reinforce the behavior of an individual
and how they accomplished it maybe more
than the technical excellence of in a
way so I want to be able to say hey if
if you are broadening your education and
you're trying something new if you are
sharing your knowledge to others if you
are stepping out of your your head down
coding role and your your coming out
with new ideas I'm trying to reward
those things
as as much as I was would reward let's
say immense effort of hours to for a
team to get there to the Finish Line you
certainly have to recognize that but
there's also Behavior recognition that I
really think is important because we
we'd make a show out of it everybody
gets a donnut and here's a here's a
little plaque for this individual and
here's what we're recognizing oh other
folks you know I like the doughnut but I
want to get the plaque too someday and
we move those folks along in their own
interest to do better by by rewarding
the right things well and that kind of
leads into the last section of the book
which is about leadership and
encouraging Engineers is the first major
topic you discussed there and you kind
of just leaned right into that so again
here we are it just keeps we keep kind
of flowing right through the book which
is great so what are some other ways
that you encourage Engineers to be
successful in what they do when I
started I had one manager who I would I
would say might be the anti-
encouragement thing he was like learning
hitting from Tai C hey Ty how how do you
how do you do that you pick up the bat
you grip it hard you swing it and you
hit the GD ball over there somewhere
okay nothing Ty yeah yeah thanks a lot I
I I can't do it that way and so we had
to graduate from Beyond the uh that kind
of encouragement it's your job just do
it because these individuals being very
talented uh would like to see their best
talents used and become visible so what
is my encouragement to an individual it
came in two ways one is to say hey
you're really good at this I don't want
you to diminish this at all keep doing
that that's fantastic so that's one type
of encouragement and the other is where
I might see a hidden flare of talent in
an individual to say just just like my
communication Talent was encouraged by
some leaders when they say Hey you write
some funny stuff can you can you apply
that to it my encouragement for someone
else to be I'm GNA create a no no
penalties zone for you to try this
you're gonna try if you fail on it
that's okay we don't care I want to see
how you do with it so sometimes
encouragement was setting them up for
the Poss possibility of failure but if
they did fail they're like well at least
I tried you know and and I learned
something from it but some of the best
successes came from those folks
realizing hidden talents all of a sudden
they they would transform themselves in
a whole different uh employee and
resource for your team and that type of
confidence that I talked about how do
you how do you get their confidence
higher that is definitely one of them to
just let them try it and if they don't
fail at it they all of a sudden no that
ain't going to kill me I'm going to try
that again or you set up the fact that
failure is a learning experience and
it's okay to fail in this context and
that's another way I would frequently in
fact almost weekly in my communication
talk about here's the way I I did it
wrong and I think I had one in there I
was trying to open a bottle of pickles
or something like that and I threw it
all over my my poor sister-in-law's
kitchen and every year I pick up a can
of pickles now her husband still calls
me out he like put down the pickles put
down the pickles so you just s okay
don't do that a guy with the smallest
hands tries to open the big kosher dill
bottle all right don't do that and I use
those kind of examples to say yeah maybe
there's some things I shouldn't you know
don't lend to my talents but maybe I can
try it and if if I do try it I'll clean
up the mess if it didn't sure and
there's a culture element there too
right like reframing what happened and
taking some of the teeth out of it maybe
it's reminds me of the Thomas Edison
concept of you know I've just found a
thousand ways not to build a light
bulb yeah yeah he knows what not to do
now
I'm very much a cause and effect guy I
think some of my best technical
techniques was learned by being forced
to figure out my own mistake and figure
out how to correct it the best practice
seems to come then you get a more
resilient solution that just is going to
work longer and better and it's only
because you did something really
uninformed or even dumb to start but
that's okay that's right knowledge is
learning from your own mistakes wisdom
is learning from other people's mistakes
that's where we really want to get so
another thing you talk about this
section you say Change Is Awesome except
for engineers so this hits home I think
but share a little bit about what you
mean with that phrase yeah I know what
Moses felt like let's say hey I'm gonna
lead everybody across the desert might
take us 40 years I would just say hey
guys change management we are here we
take somebody's doing a job with a
pencil and paper when I started and now
you're people are doing things on a
Mainframe I'm bringing it to the web
people are doing things on the web I'm
bringing it to mobile phones and devices
and I don't have the chip plugged into
my head yet but I'm figuring that's
coming someday too I'll have a new user
interface that way and so what I would
try to tell them is like hey remember
all those people when you were
introducing your new system they said
I'm not going to use this thing this
thing looks weird or it doesn't work the
way the old one works and you would say
but this is the way to go this is this
will help you I'm telling them the same
thing that the change management of the
individuals hey I've got 10 years
experience you know what that looks like
on my resume it's great this company is
now asking to learn something else and
your resume will be even greater when
you get done with it and we're going to
help you through it so in a way the
change management within engineering is
to give them that hey you're still just
as valuable as you were before and more
so because you're going to continue to
move the organization forward you're
going to lead at the front you're not
going to back into Tech you're going to
take hold of it and and use it for our
our betterment and we're going to reward
you for it so change management I wasn't
the kind of guy that says 'you going to
learn this or else because we did have
so much Legacy software and we needed
some folks to do that but I was really
specific in my praise even promotions
about the fact that folks are trying new
and difficult things and change
management is just part of the the
business very few folks can start with
one technology and end with it and those
who do that might not have very long
careers as well so what would be your
encouragement to someone who finds
himself in a situation where they are
being encouraged to shift from maybe
being an individual contributor into a
more formal leadership role and and a
couple things in that one how would you
help them with the decision process
about whether to pursue that or not and
second if they choose to pursue it what
would you encourage them to learn and do
in order to grow into that role if they
don't have any formal training oh wow
what an awesome question so you get to a
juncture where you've probably conquered
in your own talents the technical things
that you can possibly do you've probably
done some of the most difficult things
possible and in my case I was just
loaded with you know a nice history of
of good accomplishments and a leader
joined the organization who didn't know
anything about it talked to some people
he says he came over and said to me hey
you're leading this technical effort how
about you try and teach engineers in
general to do what you're doing so we
end with five of you 10 of you are you
sure you want 10 of me was first my
first
reaction and he says well not
specifically like you but I want these
behaviors and so my charge that was
encouragement for me right you have
certain good behaviors I would like to
promote and here's what we're going to
do with you to put you in the spotlight
so they put a microphone in my hand in
front of several hundred people I'm like
okay I'm definitely not qualified for
this I've been sitting in the back room
all these years so I had to learn
certain things they got me a speech
coach even that says look you're so
goofy we're going to try and get you to
speak better and give these ideas out
because we want to show others that a
career can extend into leadership and
you still have your technical skills but
you're now going to lead more and more
people to the right Technologies the
right behaviors the right practices uh
something called non-functional
requirements was was something I I got
to build from the ground up and it was
just a yard stick to measure how are we
doing doing as an engineering community
and we could see it as a glance how is
anyone's system doing it was important
to be able to say for me okay this is
this is how I see you happening from the
management side and here are the
challenges where we can improve if you
like that type of work if you like
guiding others to have a success and
then be able to cheer the fact that
they've hit the finish line and want a
metal leadership is probably right for
you if it really worries you to be in
the visible mode to be out front talking
to people and encouraging them it's just
not for some people then the technical
career can be continually rewarding for
you you could be a technical lead and
leading people means you're just going
to want to go out and create more great
behavior and more successes Beyond
yourself so what about those who find
themselves in the formal leadership role
even though they might feel
uncomfortable or like they aren't really
suited to it but that's just sort of
where they've ended up yeah my first one
was probably like that I was
implementing in a in an area where I had
70 some people that were all doing
technical stuff and I was not by title
but I was actually doing the job and
they said hey here's what we're going to
do we're going to put you in pure
management for a bit we want you to
forward this new technology to
production and and get the team to do
things the right way and I I realized
once I got there like oh my gosh you
mean I've actually learned something by
by being a technical leader for a while
and helping people along this also
applies just fine to guiding people in
their careers to guiding people in the
right behaviors to have more the soft
skills I had to develop the right way to
say things the ways of not to make
people angry and and Trigger emotions I
had a lot of work to do there but it all
came down to really wanting the best for
the team and the people there and if if
you can look at it from that perspective
I'm here to help these folks become
better at what they do the day gets so
much easier and it isn't so much of hey
I'm the hiring and firing guy I'm the
disciplinarian not really no if if
you're spending all your time and
discipline then something isn't right
and and that's my chance to look in the
mirror again absolutely you mentioned
something interesting before you said
that they actually got you a speech
coach or something along those lines and
I I wonder what other soft skill areas
you might
encourage people who find themselves in
a software leadership role but maybe
weren't formally trained what what are
some specific things that's one improve
your communication your by the way I've
also had the same thing so that's one
but what else what other soft skills
would you recommend that they develop
yeah there's so many ways to improve
those things one of my introductions
into leadership was in in a church
Council hey you're kind of smart why
don't we put you on the church Council I
don't know if that's a good idea I'm an
engineer I like trust us we think you'd
be okay
and and so I was able to improve my
written and verbal skills by being able
to share in a round table and talk about
the different people that that ended up
on this Council it was great I got to
see people from all sorts of walks of
life and skills but all hoping that our
church continues helpfully so so
volunteer efforts are great for that
sort of thing it doesn't have to be
complicated it doesn't have to be
stressful it can just be hey maybe I'm
good at this I'm going to try it out and
so I I think volunteer efforts are
excellent anything that that helps your
communication skills there were
sometimes I could look at one of my kids
and I couldn't come up with their name
for a few seconds because my head was in
coat I would actually still be so far in
that side of my brain I could like all
right I know your name is you're a girl
and you're this old therefore you must
be you know it would take me three
seconds to come up with it so how do I
transition my brain back and forth more
easily how do I not get locked into
technical thinking well quite often uh
things you can do in the volunteer world
that that makes that happen writing
fiction was a great thing for me hey can
you put yourself in the shoes of other
people here's a character who's an old
grumpy guy well now I'm that guy so I
guess I can't say I'm in those shoes but
when I was younger I was writing about
people in other shoes and I'm saying
here's here's what they think like and
over time I thought how wrong that was
certain things that I was writing down
wasn't right at all and my my
stereotypes weren't right well that was
a great lesson sure what are some future
Trends you see for software engineers
and leaders yeah I think that the low
code world was interesting to me I I
stood up in front of a a coding
Conference of 250 people and I told them
low code's coming and you better learn
something about it and they boo that
kind of stuff because they were all
coders doesn't mean you're not going to
code but certain parts of your
applications low code makes sense
multi-channel delivery why don't you let
it figure all that out for you and not
code everything in JavaScript yourself
so I I'm a big proponent of that I think
that AI has its place but I'm also one
of those worried people that if we start
using AI within Engineering in certain
ways we're going to be in trouble as
well so AI give me a routine that does X
it gives me this routine I put it in my
system 10 years later there's a lawsuit
saying you have a copyright man some AI
wrote part of your system and we want
some of your billions of dollars so I
think that having an awareness of the
right place for AI as a trend for the
future is going to be super important
and using it in the right ways is uh
will be critical to Engineers this is
where I get back into the ethics and the
like hey am I being ethical and how I'm
using tools AI is going to be a
Temptation and it will be a Temptation
for both leaders and Engineers so I I
think an appreciation of that is is key
and then finally the the continued
vigilance of information security
protecting our systems it just never
stops it's an arms race where the bad
guys get better and the good guys will
need to get better to to defend the
system so all those things I I think is
where we'll be spending a lot of time of
course now I'm hearing Star Wars
darkness rises and light to meet
it I I we've heard that anytime somebody
learns a new tech hey come over to the
dark side all right that's right all
over well chuck if people want to find
out more about what you're up to where
can they go I am out on LinkedIn Charles
windorf engineer has some of my my
latest work I do have a science fiction
novel series coming out so Charles
windorf out on Amazon mid year you'll
start to see a series of six books uh
come out there and I do expect uh still
to be writing about uh both fiction and
in it leadership so there is a Charles
windorf domcom is out there as well okay
great thanks so much for joining me
today Chuck Jeff this has been great a
lot of fun doing this awesome this is
Jeff dle for software engineering thanks
for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by It
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
scr.cr is licensed under cre cretive
commment license
2.5 thanks for listening